Mss.B.F113 Mss.B.F113 Mss.B.F113
American Philosophical Society
Giovanni Valentino Mattia Fabbroni papers, ca. 1770s-1875
Circa 1770-1875
Mss.B.F113
American Philosophical Society
8.0 Linear feet
This collection includes letters from, and drafts of letters to, scientists, artists, musicians, soldiers, political figures, and court personages throughout Europe, especially Italy and France. Topics covered range from personal and social affairs to agriculture, botany, geology, natural history, coinage, museum management, politics, weights and measures, current affairs. The collection also includes four diaries, housed separately with manuscript volumes.
Ca. 8500 items. Includes four volumes housed with manuscript volumes in vault
Fabbroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822
Box 1-16
Arrangement note
The index is an alphabetical listing of material and reflect the physical arrangement of the collection. The index is not complete. The collection is composed of folders which group letters by author, and some letters may not be listed.
Portions of the collection are composed of letters between Fabroni and Filippo Mazzei. This portion is given the call number addition ".m". This is visiable in the index.
Early American History Note
This Collection of Giovanni Fabbroni letters contain a range of correspondence that Fabbroni carried on with fellow scientists throughout Europe. Although much of Fabbroni’s travel and correspondence focused on Continental Europe, his wide-ranging correspondence can offer insight into the British Atlantic World and the flow of ideas and information within it.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Received and accessioned, 1961. See in-house shelf list for additional accession dates and numbers.
Biographical/Historical note
Giovanni Valentino Fabbroni (1752-1822) was an Italian naturalist, agronomist, economist, and politician. He was a founder and vice director of the Natural History Museum in Florence and also served as director of the Mint of Tuscany. His varied activities included electrochemical experiments that helped pave the way for subsequent developments, most significantly the invention of the battery; studies in currency, including contributions to the creation of the metric system; and proposals related to agricultural and economic reform in Tuscany. Fabbroni maintained an extensive correspondence with a wide variety of individuals in Europe and the United States.
Little is known about Fabbroni’s personal life, including his upbringing and education; a hint that he may have come from less then favorable circumstances is provided by R. Lee who wrote in her Memoirs of Baron Cuvier (1833) that, “Like most of those who have attained great celebrity, the early years of M. Fabbroni were passed in struggle and difficulty.” He was born in 1752 in Florence, Italy, where he also spent most of his adult life. In 1775, he collaborated with Felice Fontana (1730-1805) in the founding of the “Imperiale e Regio Museo di Fisica e Storia Naturale,” a natural history museum. For the next thirty years, Fabbroni served as the museum’s vice director under Fontana, who was appointed its first director.
Fabbroni was an advocate of the chemical revolution of Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier (1742-1794, APS 1775) and at the museum, which had its own laboratory, he and Fontana conducted research in pneumatic chemistry and electrochemistry. One of his research interests concerned animal electricity, which had only recently been demonstrated by Luigi Galvani (1737-1798). Fabbroni proposed that galvanism may be due solely to chemical affinities, and that electricity could be generated only by the contact of dissimilar bodies when they reacted together chemically, differed in temperature, or were rubbed together. Fabbroni’s findings, which he presented before the Accademia dei Georgofili in 1793, set the stage for a favorable reception in 1800 of Alessandro Volta's (1745-1827) voltaic pile, the first battery that produced a reliable, steady current of electricity. Fabbroni’s ideas also influenced the work of Anthony Carlisle (1768-1842), William Nicholson (1753-1815) and Humphry Davy (1778-1829, APS 1810), who may have learned of them from translations of Fabbroni’s paper published in the Journal de physique (1799), the Journal of Natural Philosophy (1800), and the Philosophical Magazine (1800). Fabbroni also often assisted Grand Duke Peter Leopold (1747-1792), who conducted scientific experiments as a hobby.
In 1778 Fabbroni wrote the first of many letters to Thomas Jefferson. Jefferson had learned of Fabbroni from their mutual friend Philip Mazzei (1730-1816) as early as 1767, and he had encouraged the young man to move to Virginia to become music teacher and tutor to his children. Fabbroni evidently was inclined to accept the offer when the Duke of Tuscany selected him to travel through England and France to observe scientific and technological progress in each nation. Frabbroni accepted the Duke’s invitation, and while there is no evidence that he ever visited the United States, he subsequently corresponded with Jefferson on a variety of topics, including meteorology and music, which Jefferson famously described in a letter to the Italian as "the favorite passion of my soul.”
In 1778 Fabbroni traveled to England, where he recorded his observations in a series of diaries. During his stay in London he became acquainted with Benjamin Franklin as well as Richard Price (1723-1791, APS 1785), Joseph Priestley (1733-1804, APS 1785), Benjamin Vaughan (1751-1835, APS 1786), and other radicals, many of whom were members of the Club of Thirteen, an intellectual club founded in the 1770s. Fabbroni apparently attended some of their meetings and he also carried their letters and parcels to Paris.
In 1780 Fabbroni published in Paris his Reflexions sur l'état actuel de l'agricolture, in which he developed new techniques of agronomy and cultivation based on procedures of pneumatic chemistry. He suggested, for example, replacing crop rotation and tilling with a series of plants grown together. The book had a considerable impact on farming in Tuscany. More generally, Fabbroni's work contributed to the process of applying chemistry to study the plant world, which eventually developed into the disciple of agricultural chemistry.
In 1783 Fabbroni became a member of the Accademia dei Georgofili, a learned society dedicated primarily to the natural sciences and agricultural reform, and the following year he commenced work as its correspondence secretary, acting as the intermediary between the Accademia and the museum. In addition, the Tuscan government frequently called on Fabbroni to contribute plans and ideas toward the improvement of Tuscany’s economy, including the location of potentially lucrative coal deposits. The scholarly works he published during this period include essays on topics such as currency, economics, and government.
Fabbroni was influential in the development of the metric system and in its introduction to Italy. In the late 1790s the French government sought to establish a mass standard that would aid in the regulation of commerce. Fabbroni was selected as a member of a committee charged with determining the mass of a cubic decimeter of water. At the time the decreed definition of the kilogram specified water at 0°C, its highly stable temperature point. In 1799, after several years of research, Fabbroni and the French chemist Louis Lefèvre-Gineau (1751-1829) redefined the temperature at which water reaches maximum density as 4°C, as opposed to 0°C. Based on their calculations, a new Kilogram was manufactured and delivered to the Archives of the Republic. The prototype was ratified, and the new standard eventually stood for the next ninety years.
Overall, Fabbroni’s activities were unsually varied. Lee wrote in her biography of Fabbroni’s friend Georges L. C. F. D. Cuvier (1769-1832), who evidently penned an eulogy for Fabbroni, that “we find [Fabbroni], at one time, charged with delicate political missions; at others, with the direction and administration of the mint at Florence [1800]; seeking the causes of pestilence, and the means of prevention; making roads, fixing conductors for lightning, and aiding the state by his counsels.” His diverse interests are also reflected in Fabbroni’s long and varied list of correspondents, ranging from artists to soldiers, aristocrats to scientists, and politicians to economists. His correspondents include, for example, Davy, Mazzei, Cuvier, Priestley, Sir Joseph Banks (1743-1820), Johann Reinhold Forster (1729-1798, APS 1793), Alexander von Humboldt (1769-1859, APS 1804), Angelica Kauffmann (1741-1807), and the Marquis de Lafayette (1757-1834, APS 1781).
Fabbroni died in 1822 in Pisa, Italy.
Aldini, Giovanni, 1762-1834; Amoretti, Carlo, 1741-1816; Anisson-Dupéron, Alexandre-Jacques-Laurent, 1776-1852; Arcet, Jean-Pierre-Joseph d', 1777-1844; Banks, Joseph, Sir, 1743-1820; Boscovich, Roger Joseph, 1711-1787; Botta, Carlo, 1766-1837; Brugnatelli, Luigi Vincenzo, 1761-1818; Charles, Jacques Alexandre César, 1746-1823; Court de Gébelin, Antoine, 1725-1784; Crell, Lorenz Florenz Friedrich von, 1744-1816; Cuvier, Georges, Baron, 1769-1832; Dandolo, Vincenzo, conte, 1758-1819; Davy, Humphry,Sir,1778-1829.; Deleuze, J. P. F., (Joseph Philippe François), 1753-1835; Fabbroni, Leopoldo Pelli; Favi, Francesco; Fontana, Felice, 1730-1805; Forster, Georg, 1754-1794; Forster, Johann Reinhold, 1729-1798; Gallerio, Giorgio; Gallini, Stefano, 1766-1836; Grégoire, Henri, 1750-1831; Grimaldi, Gabriele; Hervey, Frederick Augustus, 1730-1803; Humboldt, Alexander von, 1769-1859; Humboldt, Wilhelm, Freiherr von, 1767-1835; Ingenhousz, Jan, 1730-1799; Kauffmann, Angelica, 1741-1807; La Cépède, M. le comte de, (Bernard Germain Etienne de La Ville sur Illon), 1756-1825; La Rochefoucauld-Liancourt, François-Alexandre-Frédéric, duc de, 1747-1827; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834; Lalande, Joseph Jérôme Le Fran, 1732-1807; Magalhães, João Jacinto de, 1722-1790; Mazzei, Filippo,1730-1816.; Penrose, Thomas, 1742-1779; Potocki, Jan,hrabia,1761-1815.; Priestley, Joseph, -- 1733-1804. -- Unitarianism explained and defended.; Raddi, Giuseppe, 1770-1829; Raspe, Rudolf Erich, 1737-1794; Sacco, Luigi, 1769-1836; Santi, Giorgio; Saunders, William, 1743-1817; Savi, Gaetano, 1769-1844; Smithson, James, 1765-1829; Solander, Daniel Charles, 1733-1782; Targioni Tozzetti, Ottaviano, 1833-1909; Tessier, M., (Alexandre-Henri), 1741-1837; Thiébaut de Berneaud, Arsenne, 1777-1850; Thunberg, Carl Peter, 1743-1828; Vassalli-Eandi, Antonio Maria, 1761-1825; Venturi, Giovanni Battista, 1746-1822; Wedgwood, Josiah, 1730-1795; Whitehurst, John, 1713-1788; Agriculture; Beyond Early America; Botany.; Bridges.; Coinage.; Diaries.; Foreign Language; France -- Intellectual life.; France -- Politics and government -- 1774-1793.; France -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; France -- Social life and customs.; Geology.; Italy -- Intellectual life.; Italy -- Politics and government -- 18th century.; Italy -- Politics and government -- 19th century.; Italy -- Social life and customs.; Locks (Hydraulic engineering) -- Middle Atlantic states -- History.; Machinery -- Drawings.; Manufacturing processes.; Museums -- History.; Natural history.; Science and Technology; Scientific Correspondence; Sketches.; Tools -- Drawings.; Weights and measures.
- Papers
  - Letter to [Giovanni Fabroni, 1789-1796; B F113; 9x7-1/4; [Banks, Sir John, bart., 1743-1820.]
    Scope and Contents note
    ca. A.L. 1p. Seal. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning a coin sent by Fabroni.
  - Letter to Jean Fabroni, Florence, April 6, 1784; B F113; 9x7-1/2; [Banks, Sir Joseph, bart., 1743-1820.]
    A.L. 4p.,add. (see Fabroni papers.) Sends seeds, given by Forsyth. Botany. Comments on Hutchins experiments on mercury at Hudson's Bay: Royal Society award.
  - Letter to Jean Fabroni, Jan. 21, 1783; B F113; 4-1/2x7; [Bicchierai, Alessandro, 1734-1797.]
    L.in 3rd.P. 1p.and add. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Recommends English friends.
  - Letter to [Giovanni Fabroni], B F113; 7-1/4x5; [Clarke, Henri Jacques Guillaume, 1765-1818.]
    19 Brumiare L.in 3rd.P. 1p. In French. (see Fabroni papers.) Invitation to dinner.
  - Letter to [Giovanni] Fabroni, Florence, Oct. 10, 1782; B F113; 8-3/4x6-3/4; [Court de] Gebelin, [Antoine], 1725-1784.
    A.L.S. 2p. and add. In French. (see Fabroni papers.) Introduces Biancourt. Notifies him of the publication of his 9th volume.
  - Letter to [Giovanni] Fabbroni [sic], B F113; 8x5; [Davy, Sir Humphry, 1778-1829.]
    Sunday. A.L.in 3rd.P. 1p.and add. (see Fabroni papers.) Thanks for his kindnesses while in Florence.
  - Letter to Jean Fabroni, B F113; 9-3/4x7-1/2; [Degérando, Joseph Marie, barton,1772-1842
    Monday morning. L. 1p.and add. In French. (see Fabroni papers.) Tells him the operation was a success.
  - Diary and commonplace book while in England, Aug. 26, May 30, [1779?], [1780?]; B F113 FILM 1391; 7x5; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.D. 14 leaves, some with sketches. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Contains extracts from, or references to publications or works, of Walsh, Forster, Magellan, Ingenhousz, Royal Society, on torpedoes, comets, science, electricity chemistry, screw, steam engines, etc.
  - Diary of visit to England, with sketches of machinery, locks, brides, manufacturing processes, etc., [1778-1779]; B F113.d FILM 1391; 7x4-1/2; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.D. 1vol.of 45 leaves, of which 43 contain writing or sketches. Concerning canals and locks, chemistry,mineralogy,glass,kilns,oil,iron,wine,button manufactory,silver works,tilt mill, grinding mills, dye-works,fertilizers, coal mines, etc.
  - Letter to [Roger Joseph] Boscov[ich;], 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 2p. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning a telescope for him and note by Nairne. Refers to chemistry, Priestley and religion.
  - Letter to Boulton & Wat[t], London, Nov. 27, 1821; B F113; 12-1/2x8; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    L. 1p. Draft on reverse of an address leaf. In French. (see Fabroni papers.) Inquires as to cost of steam apparatus for minting money.
  - Letter to [Jean] D'arcet, April 2, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. Draft. 2p. In French and English. (see Fabroni papers.) Describes experiment and its results, studying phlogiston in air, and use of nitric acid. Refers to Middleton: salt in sea-water, etc.
  - Letter to [Jean] Darcet, June 6, [1779]; B F113; 4-1/2x10-1/4, 12x9; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 9p. In French. Draft. Copy of 2p. (see Fabroni papers.) Praises Rouelle as a great chemist; sorrows for him. Writes on medicine and chemistry in England: refers to Haley, Cavendish, Priestley, Hawkins. Praises Priestley's works and hopes they will be translated in to French. Geology. Has works of Bergmann of Sweden.
  - Letter to [Jean] Darcet, [1779?]; B F113; 5x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 7p. Draft. In French. (see Fabroni papers.) Darcet's and Bergmann's study of chemistry of the diamond. Scientific life in England of medicine and chemistry, with references to Banks, John Hunter, Priestley. Refers also to Rouelle.
  - Letter to [Jean] Darcet, [1799?]; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In French. (see Fabroni papers.] Introduces Alstroemer and refers to his collection of minerals, knowledge of natural history, chemistry. Refers to Rouelle.
  - Letter to [Joseph Marie Degérando]., B F113; 6x4; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 1p. In French. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning the commission on weights and measures.
  - Letter to Favi(?), Feb. 5, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 3p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning lee and botany. Refers to Higgins, Banks and Solander.
  - Letter to Favi, Feb. 12, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    London, A.L. 2p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) News of the dispute involving Palliser, Keppel and Lord George Germain.
  - Letter to Favi, March 1, 1779; B F113; 4-1/2x10-3/4; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 1p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Introduces a friend who is a friend of Priestley and who brings the breadfruit. Asks that a letter of introduction to Tuscany be written for him.
  - Letter to Favi, March 23, [1779?]; B F113; 4-1/2x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning Priestley and phlogiston. Concerning botanical matters. Refers to Lee and Forster. Concerning publications for England.
  - Letter to Favi, April 9, 1779; B F113; 4-1/2x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 3p. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning death of Miss Ray, "La concubine di Lord Sandwich." Refers to Lee. Explains why he has not sent the telescope to Florence.
  - Letter to Favi, April 13, [1779]; B F113; 4-1/2x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 2p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni Papers.) Concerning Fontana. Refers to Forster
  - Letter to Favi, May 30, 1779; B F113; 4-1/2x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 6p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Natural history and natural philosophy. Refers to Royal Society expeditions.
  - Letter to Favi, May?, [1779]; B F113; 4-1/2x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 1p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Botany.
  - Letter to Favi, June 15, [1799]; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 8p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Lee and seeds. Chemistry, Priestley, medicine and botany.
  - Letter to Favi, Sept., [1779?]; B F113; 5x10-1/2; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 5p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Comments on what he has learned while travelling in England. Plans for the future.
  - Letter to Favi, Dec. 11, [1779?]; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning English visits. Telescopes. Refers to Priestley, Boscovich, Hunter, and medicine.
  - Letter to [Richard Kirwan;]., 1780; B F113; 8-3/4x6; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 2p. Draft. In French. Chemistry. Phlogiston. Botany. Refers to Scopoli.
  - Letter to Filippo Mazzei, Pisa, Nov. 1, 1809; B F113; 9-3/4x7-1/4; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    Florence, A.L.S.: Nanni. 1p.and add. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Member of corps-legislatif. Concerning plough and Jefferson.
  - Letter to Signor Niccoli, March 16, [1779]; B F113; 4-3/4x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 2p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning botany. Forwards bread-fruit. Refers to Capt. Cook, Favi, etc. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to A[bate] Nic[coli], May 4, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Seeds and botany. New invention for drilling. Comments on the American Revolution.
  - Letter to Ab[at]e Nicc[oli], June 24, 1779; B F113; 4-1/2x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 8p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Refers to a publication on mineralogy. Concerning agriculture in England, Tuscany and Russia. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Abate] Niccoli, Aug. 3, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 7p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Describes his travels in England and comments on manufacturing there. Lists expenses of travelling.
  - Letter to Ab[at]e Niccoli, Aug. 24, 1779; B F113; 4-1/2x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) His visit in England. English agricultural publications. Banks and Solander are helping him in natural history and botany.
  - Letter to A[bate] Nicc[oli], Sept. 7, 1779; B F113; 4-1/2x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 9p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Comments on travels in England, with special references to calculating machines steam engines of Boulton and Watts, etc.
  - Letter to [Abate] Niccoli, Sept. 20, 1779; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 8p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Cultivation of potatoes in England and their importance in agriculture. Botany. Steam engines and manufacturing in England Refers to Boulton.
  - Letter to A[bate] N[iccoli;]., 1779?; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) His experiences in England, with references to chemistry, Higgins, John Walker, Fontana, etc.
  - Letter to A[bate] N[iccoli;]., [1779?]; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 2p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning his trip and expenses. Refers to chemistry and Dr. Higgins.
  - Letter to A[bate] Niccoli, [1779?]; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 3p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning chemistry and medicine. Refers to Higgins and Banks.
  - Letter to [Joseph] Priestley, May 26, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 16p. In French. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Praises his work on phlogiston. Phlogiston may be cause of volcanic eruptions. Experiments on air with nitric acid, coal, gun-powder, etc., and results. Mentions Darcet.
  - Letter to [Joseph] Priestley, Aug. 17, [1779]; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 17p. In French. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Phlogiston: inhalation and exhalation of plants. Need to know all one can about air and comments on tools and experiments needed and known. Refers to Bergmann.
  - Letter to [Joseph] Priestley, [1780?]; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. In French. 5p. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Regrets his departure from England. Comments on experiments on air [phlogiston] and Fabroni's work on agricutlre. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to [Giorgio?] Santi, [1779]; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 7p. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning phosphorus. Chemistry. Refers to Fontana, Nollet, Forster, Higgins, etc.
  - Letter to [Clemento] Vannetti, [1779]; B F113; 5x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 10. In Italian. Draft. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning English architecture, chemistry, and agriculture. Priestley and his experiments on phlogiston. Refers to Boscovich and Forster.
  - Letter to [Gilbert] White, Nottingham, Aug. 25, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10-3/4; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 4p. Draft. In French. (see Fabroni papers.) Outlines tour of England and asks if they can meet at Etruria. Priestley's experiments on phlogiston. A new publication on air refutes Hewson on blood. Crawford's book on animal heat.
  - Letter to ----, Jan. 19, 1779; B F113; 4-3/4x10; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]
    A.L. 6p. Draft. In Italian. (see Fabroni papers.) Concerning botany, breadfruit, publications, Royal Society, etc. Refers to Charles and J.R.Forster, Solander, Banks, etc. Friendly letter.
  - Letter to ----, [1779]; B F113; 4-1/2x11; [Fabroni, Giovanni Valentino Mattia, 1752-1822.]